Alright, so another trait of a dysfunctional director
is having an overbearing and domineering style that
suppresses dissent or diversity of opinion.
Unfortunately, in certain instances, the chairman is the
one that exhibits this domineering style or failure
to want to accept dissenting views on the
board.
Another feature of a dysfunctional director is that
who wants to be the CEO always second
-guessing or trying to micromanage the CEO.
A director that breaches confidentiality before the meeting
is over, he or she is sending text
messages to people outside of the meeting who
doesn't keep the board's confidence and some people
that we consider to be board veterans, they've
been on the boards for so many years
and they feel that they know if they've
done it, they have the t-shirt.
So what does the board then do having
identified a dysfunctional director?
First of all, before the board can come
to the conclusion that the director is dysfunctional,
it's best that this conclusion is arrived at
in an objective manner and one of the
ways of doing that is by the board
evaluation.
So periodically, the board would have an evaluation
of its performance and that evaluation includes a
peer review of each director's performance and if
the results of the peer review indicates that
a particular director has been adjudged by his
peers as being dysfunctional, this is an objective
test and so the chair of the board
is expected to have a conversation with such
a director, I mean making them aware of
how they've been assessed or viewed by their
peers and oftentimes that conversation achieves the purpose
for which it was intended.
At other times it doesn't, some training or
coaching might be required to help the director
bridge the gaps that have been identified because
sometimes people are just not aware that they
have such deficiencies.
The extreme or the most stringent action is
to have the person removed from the board.
We'll recall that I had said earlier that
removal from the is no longer a palatable
option because it prevents the director from being
able to sit on another board.
So what would then happen is for the
board to encourage such a director to resign.
The question can be asked that what if
this dysfunctional director is a representative of a
significant shareholder but they are themselves representing their
shareholder on the board.
Really and truly it depends on how effective
that board is.
If it's truly a board that is effective
then regardless of whether or not the person
is representing a significant shareholder they should be
able to show the results of the board
evaluation and have the significant shareholder replace this
person on the board.
So you're not taking away their right to
appoint a representative on the board but you're
asking them to appoint a person or an
individual that will add value rather than take
away value from the board.